<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>How To Transcribe Documents with Transkribus – Introduction</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>https://readcoop.eu/transkribus/howto/how-to-transcribe-documents-with-transkribus-introduction/</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
         <p xml:lang="en" n="0"> This guide explains how to transcribe documents with Transkribus<lb/><list>
               <item>For training Handwritten Text Recognition technology</item>
               <item>For Scholarly Editions</item>
            </list> If you want to have a more general overview, have a look at our <xml:idno
               uri="https://readcoop.eu/transkribus/howto/use-transkribus-in-10-steps/">10-Steps
               Guide</xml:idno><lb/> Transkribus is a platform for the automated recognition,
            transcription and searching of historical documents, using Handwritten Text Recognition
            (HTR+) technology.<lb/> Transcripts generated with Transkribus can be:<lb/><list>
               <item>Used to train a neural network (“model”) which is capable of automatically
                  recognising printed or handwritten documents</item>
               <item>Enriched and marked-up to serve as the basis for digital editions of
                  documents.</item>
            </list> This introduction enables you to either quickly create training data for the
            automated recognition of your specific documents or to create a transcription for a
            scholarly edition.<lb/> If you already have transcribed documents available and would
            like to use them as training data for HTR, please consult our How To Use Exisiting
            Transcriptions guide.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p xml:lang="jp"> このガイドでは、Transkribusでドキュメントを翻刻する方法を説明します。<lb/><list>
               <item>手書き文字認識技術をトレーニングするために</item>
               <item>学術編集版の作成のために</item>
            </list> より一般的な概要を知りたい場合は、<xml:idno
               uri="https://readcoop.eu/transkribus/howto/use-transkribus-in-10-steps/">10-Steps
               Guide</xml:idno>をご覧ください。<lb/>
            Transkribusは、手書き文字認識（HTR+）技術を用いて、歴史的なドキュメントの自動認識、翻刻、検索を行うためのプラットフォームです。<lb/> Transkribusで作成したトランスクリプトは：<lb/><list>
               <item>印刷されたドキュメントや手書きのドキュメントを自動的に認識することができるニューラルネットワーク（モデル）の学習に使用されます。</item>
               <item>充実したマークアップを行い、ドキュメントのデジタル・エディションの基礎となります。</item>
            </list>
            この「はじめに」により、特定のドキュメントを自動認識するためのトレーニングデータを素早く作成したり、学術的な出版物のための翻刻を作成することができます。<lb/>
            すでに翻刻されたドキュメントがあり、それをHTRの学習データとして使用したい場合は、How To Use Exisiting
            Transcriptionsガイドをご参照ください。<lb/>
         </p>
         </div>
         
         <div xml:lang="en">
            <head>Introduction/ はじめに</head>
            <p>This guide explains the process of transcribing documents in Transkribus.<lb/> These
               transcripts can be used:<lb/><list>
                  <item>As training data for a Handwritten Text Recognition (HTR+) model which is
                     capable of automatically transcribing your documents.</item>
                  <item>As the basis for a digital scholarly edition.</item>
               </list> There is a simple three-step process for transcribing a document in
               Transkribus:<lb/> Step 1: Uploading<lb/><list>
                  <item>Upload your documents to the Transkribus platform</item>
               </list> Step 2: Segmentation<lb/><list>
                  <item>Run the automated segmentation tool to create baselines for your
                     document.</item>
               </list> Step 3: Transcription<lb/><list>
                  <item>Transcribe the text in the segmented lines.</item>
               </list> This form of simple transcription is sufficient for training HTR
               technology.<lb/> Note: HTR can work on both handwritten and printed documents. The
               efficiency of a model will depend on the quality of the training material (your
               manual transcription), the quality of the images and on how neat or messy the writing
               is.<lb/> There are also advanced transcription options for those working on scholarly
               editions. You can adjust the reading order of the text, use historical characters,
               add tags and metadata, expand abbreviations and more. </p>

            <head>はじめに</head>
         <p xml:lang="jp"> このガイドでは、Transkribusでドキュメントを翻刻するプロセスを説明します。<lb/> これらの翻刻は次のように使用できます：<lb/><list>
               <item>ドキュメントを自動的に翻刻するための、手書き文字認識（HTR+）モデルの学習データとして。</item>
               <item>デジタル学術出版物の基礎資料として。</item>
            </list> Transkribusでドキュメントを翻刻するには、次の3つのステップがあります：<lb/> ステップ 1：アップロード<lb/><list>
               <item>ドキュメントをTranskribusプラットフォームにアップロードします。</item>
            </list> ステップ2：セグメンテーション<lb/><list>
               <item>自動セグメンテーションツールを実行して、ドキュメントのベースラインを作成します。 </item>
            </list> ステップ3: 翻刻<lb/><list>
               <item>セグメンテーションされた行のテキストを翻刻します。</item>
            </list> この形式の単純な翻刻は、HTR技術のトレーニングには十分です。<lb/>
            注：HTRは、手書きのドキュメントと印刷されたドキュメントの両方に対応できます。モデルの効率は、学習教材（あなたが手入力する翻刻）の質、画像の質、そして文字がきちんとしているか・乱れているかに左右されます。
            また、学術編集版を扱う人のための高度な翻刻オプションもあります。テキストの読み順の調整、歴史的な文字の使用、タグやメタデータの追加、略語の展開などが可能です。 <lb/>
            また、学術的な出版物を作る人のための高度な転写オプションもあります。テキストの読み順を調整することができます。タグやメタデータの追加、略語の拡張などができます。 </p>
         </div>
            
         <div>
            <head>Upload documents to Transkribus</head>
            <p xml:lang="en">
            In order to be able to run the necessary tools on your documents they
            need to reside on the Transkribus server. This means that you need to upload them to Transkribus.<lb/>
            <note>Note: All collections and documents in Transkribus are private. Only users
               authorised by you are able to see your documents. They are not made available to the
               public.</note><lb/>
            To upload click on the “Import Documents” button in the Main
            menu.<lb/></p>
               <p> You have four options to upload documents: <list>
                  <item>Upload single document from a local folder:<list>
                     <item>This option allows you to upload documents up to 500 MB.</item>
                     <item>In order to choose this option choose “Upload Single Document”</item>
                     <item>Please make that the files to be uploaded reside in an extra folder.
                        When choosing the files for the upload you won’t be able to see the files
                        in the folder. That is normal in this case. Just mark the folder and
                        confirm with “OK”.</item>
                  </list>
                  </item>
               </list><list>
                  <item>Upload via FTP<list>
                     <item>This is suitable if you want to upload several large documents</item>
                     <item>You can upload image files, as well as PDF-documents with this
                        option</item>
                     <item>Please make sure the PDF-files are not inside a folder when using the
                        FTP-upload</item>
                  </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
                  
                  <list><item>Upload via URL of DFG Viewer METS
                     <list><item>This allows you to upload documents
                        directly from repositories which support the DFG (Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft –
                        German Science Funds) Viewer</item></list>
                  </item></list>
                  
                  <list><item>Extract and upload images from PDF<list>
                     <item>This option is
                        suitable for images you want to upload which reside in a PDF-document.</item> <item>If those
                           PDF-documents are of big size, please use the FTP-upload.</item> <item>Also, if you have JP2000
                              images in your PDFs it makes sense to go for the FTP-option.</item></list></item></list>
                  
                  <list><item>
                     Add pages to an already existing document in Transkribus:
                     <list>    
                        <item>Load the document, you would like to add pages to
                           in Transkribus</item>
                        <item>Open the document manager</item>
                        <item>Select the document again by clicking on
                           it’s name in the “Document Manager”-window</item>
                        <item>Click on the green circle icon next to
                           “Add new page(s)”</item>
                        <item>Search and add the new pages via the directory</item>
                     </list></item></list>
                  
                  <list><item>Delete documents
                     from your collection:<list>
                        <item>Select the document in the collection overview within the
                           “Server”-tab</item> 
                        <item>Click on the folder icon with the small red circle “Delete the selected
                           documents from Transkribus”.</item>
                        <item>The deleted document(s) will reside in the recycle bin
                           (icon “contains deleted documents”) for two weeks. If you have deleted a document by
                           mistake you can contact us (info@readcoop.eu) and we will be able to reactivate the
                           document within these two weeks. After this, the document will be permanently
                           deleted.</item></list></item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               
            <head>Transkribusにドキュメントをアップロードする</head>
         <p xml:lang="jp"> ドキュメントに対して必要なツールを実行するためには、ドキュメントがTranskribusのサーバー上に置かれている必要があります。したがって、最初にドキュメントをTranskribusにアップロードする必要があります。<lb/>
            <note>注意：Transkribusのすべてのコレクションとドキュメントはプライベートなものとして設定され、
               お客様が許可したユーザーのみがドキュメントを見ることができ、一般には公開されていません。</note><lb/>
            アップロードするには、メインメニューの「Import Documents」のボタンをクリックします。 </p>
            <p>ドキュメントのアップロードには4つの方法があります: <list>
               <item>ローカルフォルダーからドキュメントをアップロードする方法:<list>
                  <item>この方法では、500MBまでのドキュメントをアップロードすることができます。</item>
                  <item>このオプションを選択するには、"Upload
                     Single
                     Document"を選択してください。</item>
                  <item>アップロードするファイルは、専用のフォルダにおくようにしてください。アップロードするファイルを選択する際に、通常、フォルダ内のファイルは表示されません。フォルダを選択し、"OK"をクリックしてください。</item>
               </list>
               </item>
            </list><list>
               <item>FTP経由でアップロードする方法<list>
                  <item>複数の大きな文書をアップロードしたい場合に適しています。</item>
                  <item>この方法では、PDF文書だけでなく、画像ファイルもアップロードできます。</item>
                  <item>FTPアップロードの際には、PDFファイルがフォルダ内にないことを確認してください。</item>
               </list>
               </item>
            </list>
               
               <list><item>DFGビューアMETSのURL経由でアップロードする方法
                  <list><item>この方法では、DFG（ドイツ科学基金）ビューアをサポートするリポジトリから直接文書をアップロードできます。</item></list>
               </item></list>
               
               <list><item>PDFから画像を抽出してアップロードする方法<list>
                  <item>この方法は、PDF文書に含まれる画像をアップロードしたい場合に適しています。</item> <item>PDF文書のサイズが大きい場合は、FTPアップロードをご利用ください。</item> <item>また、PDFの中にJP2000の画像がある場合は、FTPアップロード利用するのが良いでしょう。</item></list></item></list>
               
               <list><item>
                  Transkribusで既存のドキュメントにページを追加する方法:
                  <list>    
                     <item>追加したいドキュメントをTranskribusに読み込みます。</item>
                     <item>ドキュメントマネージャーを開きます</item>
                     <item>"Document Manager"ウィンドウでドキュメントの名前をクリックして再度ドキュメントを選択します。</item>
                     <item>"Document Manager"ウィンドウでドキュメントの名前をクリックして再度ドキュメントを選択します。</item>
                     <item>new page(s) "の隣にある緑色の丸いアイコンをクリックし、ディレクトリ経由で新しいページを検索して追加します。</item>
                  </list></item></list>
               
               <list><item>コレクションからドキュメントを削除する方法:<list>
                  <item>"Server"タブ内の"Collection overview"でドキュメントを選択します。</item> 
                  <item>“Delete the selected
                     documents from Transkribus”の小さな赤い丸が付いたフォルダアイコンをクリックします。</item>
                  <item>削除されたドキュメントは2週間、ごみ箱（アイコン"conatins deleted
                     documents"）に保存されます。誤ってドキュメントを削除してしまった場合は、弊社（info@readcoop.eu）にご連絡いただければ、この2週間以内にドキュメントを再有効化することができます。2週間を過ぎると、ドキュメントは永久に削除されます。</item></list></item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>

         <div>
            <head xml:lang="en">Segmentation – Layout Analysis</head>
            <p xml:lang="en"> Once you have uploaded your documents to Transkribus, you are ready to
               start segmentation. In order to transcribe your documents in Transkribus, they must
               be segmented into text regions, lines and baselines. For the HTR to work, the text
               and image need to be connected. All the segmented elements, such as printspace, text
               region, line region or baseline are stored in the PAGE file with their coordinates. </p>
            
            <head xml:lang="jp">セグメンテーション – レイアウトの認識</head>
            <p xml:lang="jp"> ドキュメントをTranskribusにアップロードしたら、セグメンテーションの準備が整います。
               Transkribusでドキュメントを翻刻するには、ドキュメントをテキスト・リージョン（領域）、ライン（行）、
               ベースライン（罫線）の範囲をそれぞれ成形する必要があります。HTRを読み取るには、文字と画像を合致させる
               必要があります。印字されたスペース、テキスト・リージョン（領域）、ライン（行）、ベースライン（罫線）の範囲など、 
               セグメント化されたすべての要素は、座標とともに「PAGE file」に保存されます。 </p>
         </div>
         <div>   
              <head xml:lang="en">Viewing profiles</head>
              <p xml:lang="en"> Viewing profiles are available to help you with the tasks of segmentation and
               transcription. You can select between viewing profiles for “Segmentation” and
               “Transcription” by clicking the “Profiles” button in the Main menu. The
               “Segmentation” profile means that baselines are displayed in red, making it easier
               to spot any errors resulting from the automated segmentation process. The
               “Transcription” profile means that the Text Editor field will be displayed,
               allowing you to transcribe your document. Of course you can simply use the
               “default” profile to perform either task.</p>
            
               <head xml:lang="ja">プロファイルの表示</head>
               <p xml:lang="ja"> プロファイルを表示させることで、セグメンテーションや翻刻の状態を確認することができます。
                  メニューバーの「Profiles」ボタンをクリックすると、「セグメンテーションSegmentation」や
                  「翻刻Transcription」を選択することができます。「セグメンテーションSegmentation」のプロファイルでは、
                  （初期設定で水色になっている）ベースライン（罫線）の線が赤色でハイライトされ、
                  自動で読み取ったセグメンテーションのエラーを見つけやすくなります。
                  「翻刻Transcription」のプロファイルでは、（画像の下方に）テキスト編集フィールドが表示され、
                  ドキュメントの翻刻をすることができます。
                  「標準default」を選択すると（上記のハイライトを解除し）あらゆる操作ができるようになります。 </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head xml:lang="en">Automatically detect text regions, lines and baselines</head>
               <p xml:lang="en"> Select the “Segmentation” viewing profile from the Main menu. Select the “Tools”
                  tab on the left side of the screen and go to the “Layout Analysis” section. Under
                  “Method:” select “CITlab Advanced” (already preselected). Select if you would like
                  to run the layout analysis only for the current page, for distinct pages, or for
                  the whole document. Make sure “Find Text Regions” is selected. Click the “Run”
                  button. If you would like to draw the text regions by hand and then search for the
                  baselines in these regions, untick the “Find Text Regions”-option before starting
                  the layout analysis. How to draw text regions is explained further down in the
                  text.</p>
               
               <head xml:lang="jp">自動でテキストのリージョン（範囲）、ライン（行）、ベースライン（罫線）を検出させる</head>
               <p xml:lang="jp"> メニューバーの「プロファイルProfile」から、「セグメンテーションSegmentation」を選びます。 
                  画面の左側にある「ツールTools」タブを選択し、（一番上の）「レイアウト認識Layout Analysis」セクションを表示します。
                  「メソッドMethod:」で（初期設定である）「CITlabAdvanced」が選択されていることを確認します。 
                  レイアウト認識を読み込ませる範囲を、現在表示されているページ（初期設定）か、指定したページ（ページ数を入力）から選びます。
                  「テキストのリージョンを認識するFind Text Regions」（初期設定）が選択されていることを確認します。 
                  「実行Run」ボタンをクリックします。
                  翻刻するテキストのリージョン（領域）を手動で指定してから、その範囲内のベースライン（罫線）を検出させたい場合、
                  レイアウト認識を開始する前に「テキストのリージョンを認識するFind Text Regions」のチェックを外してください。
                  テキスト・リージョン（領域）を指定する方法は、別項で説明します。 </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head xml:lang="en">Correcting the results of automated segmentation</head>
               <p xml:lang="en"> Note: if you are training a HTR model, the position of text regions does not need
                  to be completely exact and the reading order of the text is not relevant. If you
                  are working on a scholarly edition where a higher degree of accuracy is required,
                  it is possible to manually correct the text as in the examples below. All tools
                  for corrections on the layout analysis can be found in the “Canvas”-menu left of
                  the image. You can check their functionality by hovering over the icon. </p>
               
               <head xml:lang="jp">自動で検出されたセグメンテーションの結果を修正する</head>
               <p xml:lang="jp"> 注：HTRモデルのトレーニングのために、テキスト・リージョン（領域）の位置は完全に正確である必要はなく、
                  テキストの読み取り順序は関係ありません。より高い精度が要求される
                  Scholarly edition(学術版）で作業している場合は、
                  以下の例のようにテキストを手動で修正することができます。
                  レイアウト分析を修正するためのツールはすべて、画面の左側にある「キャンバス」メニューにあります。 
                  アイコンにカーソルを合わせると、機能を確認できます。</p>

               <div>
                  <head xml:lang="en">A line has been missed or added by mistake</head>
                  <p> In the example above the first line had been missed by the program. If you
                     would like to add it to the existing text region: Click inside the region so
                     that it is highlighted. Drag the border of the text region as needed. </p>
                  <head xml:lang="jp">誤ってライン（行）が欠落していたり、追加してしまった場合</head>
               </div>
               <div n="2">
                  <head>A marginal note needs to be split into a separate text region</head>
                  <lb/>
                  <p> If you need to split one region into two, you can do this with buttons in the
                     Canvas menu. As shown in Figure 6, the “H-button” splits a text region
                     horizontally. The “V” button splits a text region vertically. The “L-button”
                     allows you to split a text region with customisable line. </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3">
                  <head>Remove a region which is not needed</head>
                  <lb/>
                  <p> In the example above two regions are overlapping, so one can be deleted. Click
                     on the text region you wish to delete, and click the red “Remove a shape”
                     button. </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4">
                  <head>Merge two regions</head>
                  <lb/>
                  <p> Sometimes the program creates two text regions where only one is needed. In
                     this case you can easily merge the two together. Hold down the “CTRL” button on
                     your keyboard and click on both text regions. Click the “Merges the selected
                     shapes” button in the Canvas menu. </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5">
                  <head>Correct baselines</head>
                  <lb/>
                  <p> Of course it is also possible to correct the baselines in your document. As
                     with the text regions, click on a baseline and you can drag the parts of the
                     line, split a line into two or merge two lines together. You can also delete a
                     baseline and draw a new one from scratch. Click the “+BL” button in the Canvas
                     menu. Click once to start drawing your baseline and double-click to finish your
                     line. Note: Baselines are most important for HTR; line regions do not need to
                     be corrected. </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         
         <div>
            <head>Simple transcription – for HTR+ training</head>
            <lb/>
            <p> Select the “Transcription” viewing profile from the Main menu. You will see the Text
               Editor field below the image: For each line/baseline in the image you will find a
               corresponding line in the Text Editor. The image and the text are connected in this
               way. Transcribe the text according to the language of your source document. Use the
               characters of your keyboard. You can have more than one person working on a document
               but they should not work on the same page simultaneously. You can let other
               Transkribus users see your documents by clicking the “User Manager” button in the
               “Server” tab. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Train a HTR model</head>
            <lb/>
            <p> If you wish to train a HTR model to recognise your documents, this simple
               transcription is sufficient. We recommend that you start the trainig process with
               between 5,000 and 15,000 words (around 25-75 pages) of transcribed material. If you
               are working with printed rather than handwritten text, a smaller amount of training
               data is usually required. Also using a base model can reduce the required training
               material. As base model you can use one of the publicly available models in
               Transkribus (please make sure the writing is at least similar to the one in your
               documents [e.g. of a similar date, the same language and/or style]) or one of your
               previously trained models – provided it is good enough to serve as a base model. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Advanced transcription – for a scholarly edition</head>
            <lb/>
            <div>
               <head>Reading order</head>
               <lb/>
               <p> Once a document has been segmented into text regions, lines and baselines, you
                  may need to think about the reading order of the text (this is not relevant if the
                  transcription should only serve as training material). Many handwritten documents
                  include corrections and additions added by the author, or someone else. In a
                  scholarly edition you want to keep the reading order and maybe also express the
                  fact that this text was an addition. For this purpose all segmentation elements
                  can be ordered according to a user-defined order. The default reading order
                  follows the topology of the text or line regions. All shapes are ordered according
                  to the coordinates of the top left corner of a text or line region. This
                  mechanical reading order can be changed: Click on the “Item visibility” button in
                  the Main menu, and you can then choose to show the reading order of text regions,
                  lines, baselines (or words). Once you choose to show the reading order of text
                  regions or lines, numbers will be displayed on the image of your document. By
                  clicking on one of the numbers marking the reading order, it is possible to type
                  in a new number and change the reading order accordingly. The same can be done by
                  moving the segmentation elements in the “Layout” tab. In cases where the reading
                  order of a page is completely incorrect, it is possible to reorder the text Make
                  the line reading order visible as described above Click on the “Layout” tab on the
                  left side of the screen Select the page or text region that you wish to reorder
                  Click the “R” button The reading order will be rearranged according to the
                  coordinates of the top left corner of a text or line region. After that, the lines
                  should be in right order. There can be issues with the reading order of newspaper
                  columns and similar documents. E.g. the programme assigns a reading order based on
                  the horizontal layout of lines on a page, rather than putting the lines in order
                  by column. To fix this issue, use the “V” button in the Canvas menu to split the
                  text region on the page into separate regions for each column. Once there is a
                  separate text region for each column, the reading order should automatically
                  update and be correct. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Reading order: Interline additions</head>
               <lb/>
               <p> Interline additions are a frequent way in which text is added to a document. In
                  order to generate the correct reading order, the following steps need to be
                  performed manually: Click the “Item visibility” button in the Main menu Select
                  “Show lines reading order” Select the baseline below the addition (if the addition
                  is above the line). Split the line region with the “V” button in the Canvas menu
                  exactly where the addition should be logically placed Edit the reading order so
                  that it is correct. Click on the number associated with each line region and then
                  type the correct one. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Reading order: Additions as extra notes</head>
               <lb/>
               <p> Additions which appear as extra notes (e.g. at the margins of a page) should be
                  handled in a similar way to interline additions. Note: Often such extra notes (or
                  marginalia) are not part of the reading order but are “comments” and as such are
                  on a different level to the primary reading order. It will therefore be sufficient
                  to mark them as “marginalia” in the Metadata tab. Instructions on marking-up text
                  can be found in the How to enrich transcribed documents with mark-up guide. But if
                  the extra note is really an addition to the running text and needs to be added in
                  the reading order then it can be done in the following ways: Option 1: The text
                  region can be expanded so that all baselines of the addition are also part of the
                  respective text region. Note: You can use either rather large text regions, or you
                  may use polygonal text regions. For this purpose select the “Add point to selected
                  shape” button from the Canvas menu. Following the movement of your mouse pointer
                  you can add points to the original text region and expand the shape so that it
                  also includes the addition. Afterwards the additional lines/baselines can be
                  renumbered according to their correct reading order. Option 2: You can generate
                  just one large text region for the whole page and do the line/baseline
                  segmentation manually in the correct order. In this way you will get the correct
                  reading order right from the beginning. Note: this may be the best option if you
                  are dealing with a document which has a sophisticated layout with many additions,
                  notes and deletions. Option 3: You can connect the extra text region which
                  contains the addition to the line where the addition belongs. To do this, select
                  both text regions and then click the “Links two shapes” button in the “Structural”
                  tab, within the “Metadata” tab. Note: The linking will be part of the XML file but
                  is currently not supported in the export formats. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Transcription and Virtual Keyboards</head>
               <lb/>
               <p> A transcription which will serve as a basis for a scholarly edition should make
                  more data explicit to the user and offer more contextual data than a simple
                  transcription. In this case not only machine readability (i.e. training data for
                  the HTR engine) but also human readability of the text will play an important
                  role. You can add special characters and Unicode symbols using the “Virtual
                  keyboards” button in the Text Editor field. With the “Edit…” button it is possible
                  to add shortcuts for frequently used characters and to add new Unicode characters.
                  To create a shortcut, you just need to type it in the “Shortcut” column. To add
                  new Unicode characters, you use the green plus button. In the text editor you can
                  use “Backspace” to muve text one line up and “Ctrl” + “Return” to move text one
                  line down. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Diacritics and ligatures</head>
               <lb/>
               <p> The correct transcription of diacritics and ligatures requires some expert
                  knowledge. There are two main options for handling the correct transcription of
                  these characters: Option 1: Slight normalisation according to dictionary The main
                  rule to be applied here is the following: As long as you can clearly see the base
                  character of a glyph and as long as the base character is also the one which is
                  used in the dictionary to express this glyph, keep to the base character. Example
                  1: LATIN SMALL LETTER Y will appear in many documents with an extra diacritical
                  sign, indicating the history of this character coming from ii or ij. Therefore you
                  find two dots or a something similar looking above the “y”. In simple transcripts
                  you will transcribe this as LATIN SMALL LETTER Y since the base character is
                  clearly visible. Example 2: LATIN SMALL LETTER S is expressed with two graphemes
                  in most European historical scripts. We find therefore a clear distinction between
                  LATIN SMALL LETTER S and LATIN SMALL LETTER LONG S. But although there is a clear
                  distinction, a simple transcription would use LATIN SMALL LETTER S in both cases.
                  Option 2: Palaeographic Transcription Philologists or palaeographers are not only
                  interested in the correct transcription, but also in the historical appearance and
                  development of graphemes. Therefore it might also be interesting to transcribe the
                  above examples with full support of the Unicode character set or even by utilizing
                  the private area of Unicode. Note: Please take into account that this is an
                  important decision and will affect the usability of the text in many ways. If you
                  decide to go for a palaeographic transcription it will cause a lot more work than
                  with a slightly normalized transcription. Note: In printed texts (which can also
                  be transcribed in Transkribus) the transcription of ligatures may play a role.
                  Again the same rule can be applied: Though specific combinations of letters, such
                  as “ft” are expressed with a specific grapheme where two graphemes are matched
                  together, and though such ligatures can also be expressed with specific Unicode
                  letters, we recommend transcribing them according to the dictionary. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Punctuation marks</head>
               <lb/>
               <p> Punctuation marks are transcribed in the same way as characters. Use the
                  appropriate character on your keyboard and do not normalize or add punctuation
                  marks. Typical punctuation marks are: modern characters such as dot, comma,
                  semicolon, colon: “.”, “,”, “;”:” historical characters such as virgule (slash),
                  or line fillers, etc. Note: Colons in historical texts are often used to mark
                  abbreviated words. These should be transcribed as a colon. In contrast to many
                  transcription rules where punctuation marks are added and omitted according to a
                  modern understanding we recommend to keep to the original punctuation marks. If
                  you want to add punctuation marks which do not appear in the original document you
                  may use the “supplied” tag in the “Tagging” tab, within the “Metadata” tab to
                  indicate that the punctuation mark was added by yourself. </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>References</head>
            <lb/>
            <p> To get an overview on scripts from Unicode: http://www.unicode.org/charts/ For
               historical transcriptions the following extensions are of interest: Latin Extended-B:
               http://www.unicode.org/charts/PDF/U0180.pdf Contains e.g.: Non-European and historic
               Latin Phonetic and historic letters Additions for Slovenian and Croatian etc. Latin
               Extended-C: http://www.unicode.org/charts/PDF/U2C60.pdf Contains e.g.: Orthographic
               Latin additions etc. Latin Extended-D: http://www.unicode.org/charts/PDF/UA720.pdf
               Contains e.g.: Medievalist additions Insular and Celtic letters Ancient Roman
               epigraphic letters etc. MUFI (Medieval Unicode Font Initiative) This initiative has
               collected and systematized about 1512 characters which are especially recommended for
               the transcription of medieval documents. Note: Some of them are still in the
               “private” section of Unicode, therefore not officially available.
               http://folk.uib.no/hnooh/mufi/
               http://folk.uib.no/hnooh/mufi/specs/MUFI-Alphabetic-4-0.pdf </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Credits</head>
            <lb/>
            <p> We would like to thank the many users who have contributed their feedback to help
               improve the Transkribus software. </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
